DR. KATJA DITTRICH

Psychologist – Researcher – Data Scientist

SUMMARY

I am a senior researcher in the field of clinical psychology. I am trained in R and SPSS for data handling, visualization, and modelling and currently diving deeper into Python/SQL/Git for data analysis, handling, and version control. Due to my background as a psychologist and psychotherapist I have strong communication skills and understanding of human behavior behind the data. Data becomes powerful when analyzed thoughtfully using the right techniques and communicated in comprehensive way. My experience in teaching, publication and presentation of data has taught me to effectively explain insights to a technical and non-technical audience. Due to my experience in supervision, project management, and psychotherapy I know to support people and groups in their personal and professional development. Being always eager about my own learning and development, my passion about data now leads me to focus on more data centered roles.

EXPERIENCE

Charité – Universitätsmedizin Berlin

Psychologist / Researcher November 2013 – April 2023

Cross-Project Tasks:

- Processing and analysis of data sets (SPSS, R)
- Publication of results in international professional journals and presentation to clinical audiences at national and international conferences
- Cooperation with various departments and stakeholders
- Teaching in the medical degree program (communication, teamwork)

March 2020 – April 2022

Senior Scientist

- Coordination of a multicentric care study (DEPSY) and a subproject of a multicentric intervention study (UBICA II)
- Supervision of doctoral candidates and students
- Data management and quality monitoring

Successful implementation of two multicentric studies (UBICA II and DEPSY) with limited resources. Development of a web-based database, survey tools, and study teams to execute the studies.

November 2013 – February 2020

Junior Scientist / PhD Candidate

- Data collection using interviews and questionnaires with adults and children
- Recruitment of study participants

Successful completion of two studies (UBICA and Berlin LCS), preparation of my doctoral thesis, and publication of numerous scientific articles.

- **** 0152 56184651
- P Berlin, Germany
- % www.dittrichkatja.com

Further Links:

- % LinkedIn
- % Github
- **Researchgate**

TECHNICAL SKILLS

IBM SPSS (10 years), R/R Studio (5 years, especially ggplot2, tidyverse, lavaan), Python / SQL / GitHub / Streamlit (since June 2023). Machine learning and statistics (linear, logistic, Poisson regression, path analysis, SEM, growth curves, mediation, discriminant analysis, (M)ANCOVA, factor analysis)

SOFT SKILLS

Secure and professional communication in German and English with technical and non-technical audiences. Storytelling. Project management. Independent work. Analytical and critical thinking. Problem-solving. Working in interdisciplinary teams.

EDUCATION

Psychology Degree (Diploma) Humboldt University of Berlin from October 2007 to October 2013

Doctorate in Psychology (Dr. rer. nat.) Humboldt University of Berlin in February 2020

Licensed Psychotherapist (Cognitive Behavioral Therapy) Center for Psychotherapy at Humboldt University of Berlin in April 2021

EXPERIENCE

Freiraum Psychotherapie

Psychotherapist April 2021 – March 2023

Application of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy techniques and related methods for the treatment of mental disorders.

CERTIFICATIONS

Data Science Retreat

September – December 2023

Data science bootcamp, covering topics related to machine learning, deep learning, computer vision, natural language processing, model deployment, and data visualization. Tools and languages: Python (Tensorflow, Numpy, Pandas), Git/Github.

DeepLearning.Al

September – December 2023

Machine Learning Specialization (Credential)
Deep Learning Specialization (Credential)

DataCamp

February 2023

Data Analyst with R (Credential)